[Music]
suppose the fraction a over b is less
than or equal to the fraction c
over d both of these fractions can be
represented by the slopes of hypotenuses
of right triangles and the inequality
means that the slope of the hypotenuse
of the triangle with legs a and b
is less than or equal to the slope of
the hypotenuse of the triangle with legs
c and d
aligning the two triangles this way
allows us to draw them inside of a third
right triangle
this new right triangle has legs of
length b plus d and a plus c
now comparing the slopes of the
hypotenuses of these three triangles
reveals that a over b is less than or
equal to the slope of the big triangle
which is a plus c over b plus d and that
in turn is less than or equal to the
slope of the top right triangle
which is c over d the middle quantity
a plus c over b plus d is known as the
median
of the two fractions a over b and c over
d
therefore this is known as the mediant
inequality
[Music]
you